Guide to the Doris Ulmann Photograph Collection ca. 1910-1934 PR 72
© 2011 New-York Historical Society
Doris Ulmann Photograph Collection
ca. 1910-1934
PR 72
© 2011 New-York Historical Society
223.71 Linear feet (150 boxes)
The collection consists of ca. 3000 photographic prints, primarily platinum but some photogravure. Typical portrait subjects include prominent artists, authors, the Columbia University medical faculty, Johns Hopkins University medical faculty, and American editors. There are also examples of some of her best-known African-American and Appalachian photographs. Although many of the images are unidentified, they are the largest known body of prints made by Ulmann herself
Provenance
Gift of the Doris Ulmann Foundation, 1954.
Access Restrictions
Open to qualified researchers.
Photocopying undertaken by staff only. Limited to twenty exposures of stable, unbound material per day. See guidelines in Print Room for details.
Biographical Note
Doris Ulmann was a prolific and accomplished photographer who was born in New York in 1882. She lived and worked there until her death in 1934 at the age of 52. Ulmann produced compelling images of rural life in the Southeastern United States, as well as portraits of the prominent American authors, artists, actors, editors, and physicians of her time. Ulmann's photographs were widely published in periodicals and biographical compilations during her lifetime. Three limited-edition portrait books were illustrated by Ulmann, featuring composed images in urban professional settings: The Faculty of the College of Physicians & Surgeons, Columbia University in the City of New York (New York: Paul B. Hoeber, 1919); A Book of Portraits of the Faculty of the Medical Department of the Johns Hopkins University, Baltimore (Baltimore: The Johns Hopkins Press, 1922); and A Portrait Gallery of American Editors (New York: William Edwin Rudge, 1925). But Ulmann's artistic reputation today rests largely on her work in Roll, Jordan, Roll (New York: Robert O. Ballou, 1933), which contained essays on the American South by her friend and Pulitzer prize-winning novelist Julia Peterkin, and "photographic studies" by Ulmann. Many of the photographs were made on Peterkin's husband's family farm in South Carolina, which employed over 300 African-American farmworkers.
Philip Walker Jacobs' book The Life and Photography of Doris Ulmann (University Press of Kentucky, 2001) provides the most recent and comprehensive account of Ulmann's personal and professional worlds. In his biography, Jacobs shapes Ulmann's life through previously unknown or unpublished correspondence and public records. Prior to Jacobs' book, little factual information was known about Ulmann, and the source of much of that was her assistant, John Jacob Niles. In addition to providing new information about Ulmann's early life and career, Jacobs goes to great length to document Ulmann's complex relationship with Niles, who worked for her for the last two years of her life and was at her bedside when she died. Among other details, Jacobs notes that various changes to Ulmann's will, made while Niles was her assistant, resulted in a legal dispute between Niles and Ulmann's sister and brother-in-law, Henry and Edna Necarsulmer, after her death.
An account of the disposition of Ulmann's photographs and negatives is carefully detailed in Jacobs' text and many appendices, which provide several annotated lists for easy reference, including: A Selective List of Public and Private Collections Containing Photographs, Books, and Archives By and About Doris Ulmann; A List of Doris Ulmann's Exhibitions; Published Photographs; The Medium, Edition, Identification, and Rarity of Doris Ulmann's Photographs; A Selective Index of Doris Ulmann's Photographic Subjects; and a Bibliography.
Scope and Content Note
The Doris Ulmann Photograph Collection spans the period from ca. 1910-1934 and contains 3,016 photographs and a few miscellaneous items. Each item has been entered in a detailed Microsoft Access database, which can be accessed only in the repository. More specific notes on cataloging are also available in the repository.
The great majority of the photographs are platinum prints, though there are also some oil pigment prints. It is presumed that Ulmann herself printed the original photographs in the collection, most of which are in their original mats, and many of which are signed and dated. The mats are in the standard format of the Clarence White School, where Ulmann had studied, and were made under her direction if not actually by her.
Some of the images in the collection are photogravure prints that are either printer's proofs or have been cut from the four previously mentioned published limited edition books. These can be identified in the database by searching the word "gravure" in the 'Notes' field.
Of the 3,016 images in the collection, 922 are signed by Ulmann. Of those, 646 are signed "Doris Ulmann," 272 are signed "Doris U. Jaeger," and four are signed "Doris Jaeger." Five of the images signed Doris Ulmann (numbers 122, 207, 208, 210, 212) had been signed "Doris U. Jaeger," which she erased and reinscribed "Doris Ulmann." Charles H. Jaeger was Ulmann's husband, fellow-photo-enthusiast, and a physician who was a Columbia University faculty member. The couple appears to have separated by November 1920; one year later Ulmann was exhibiting photographs under her maiden name. The Ulmann database identifies specific image numbers with signatures and various monograms, another way Ulmann signed her prints.
Ulmann dated 237 of the photographs that she signed between 1916 and 1919. All but two have the "Doris U. Jaeger" signature, with the date appearing as a full year or abbreviated: 1919 or '19, for example. Exceptions are images 212 and 2803, which have variant signatures. Again, dated images can be identified through the database.
The platinum prints in the collection are two sizes, each of which she presented differently. The smaller of the two are trimmed to 4.625 by 6.5 inches. The prints are glued to a tissue backing, the backing is glued to a light gray paperboard mount, and the mount and mat hinged together with cloth tape. The print floats inside a window that is cut to 5.625 by 7.5 inches. When signed, her signature appears in pencil on the tissue below the print on the right side.
The larger size prints are trimmed to 6 by 8 inches. The mat and mount are of the same off-white paperboard. The prints are glued to the mount and float inside a window that is cut to 6.5 x 8.5 inches. Signatures on these prints appear directly on the mount, in pencil below the photograph on the right side.
The oil pigment photographic images are 6 by 8 inches and the paper is not trimmed. They are mounted and matted, and, if signed, are inscribed like the platinum prints of this size.
The overall dimension of the matted photographs is 11.25 by 14.25 inches.
Ulmann did not identify any of her portrait subjects on the works themselves, and this collection contains none of her original records or notes to aid in identification. Approximately one-third of the sitters were identified when the collection was processed in 2002-03. Within the collection there are often many images of the same subject made during a sitting, but sometimes as many as twenty or twenty-five. Due to the collection's arrangement, these portraits are not generally found grouped together, but can be united though the database. A list of identified sitters follows the finding aid. There are no images of Doris Ulmann in the collection.
Typical subjects include American authors and artists such as Sherwood Anderson, Calvin Coolidge, Esther Forbes, Martha Graham, Sinclair Lewis, and Edna St. Vincent Millay, in addition to the hundreds of portraits of physicians from Ulmann's books for Columbia and Hopkins, as well as portraits of the editors. Most of the images published in Roll, Jordan, Roll, which are acknowledged to be some of the most artistically beautiful works she created, appear within the collection. Whether posed by Ulmann or not, the Roll, Jordan, Roll images give an exquisite visual record of former African-American slaves and their descendents as they appeared almost seventy years after the Emancipation Proclamation on this particular South Carolina plantation. However, seen in the context of what is today more generally known about the conditions of slavery, some of the images may appear highly romanticized.
Each photograph in the Doris Ulmann collection was assigned a consecutive number that corresponds to the order in which the photographs were found upon their arrival at the Society. The number is written in pencil on the front of the mat, backing, or print. Although some of the subjects are grouped together numerically, there are not enough to suggest anything other than a random arrangement previous to their arrival. The photographs were kept in number order during processing, and a database created to fully describe each photograph. In addition, photocopies were made of the photographs, and have been grouped into seven general subject categories for easy patron browsing and visual reference. The seven major subject categories are: Men; Women; Children; Groups (two or more); Landscapes; Still Lifes; and Other. The photocopies are arranged under these seven categories.
Within the database, there are five additional subset categories applied to the six broader subjects: African American, Native American, Religious People, Urban, and Country.
MEN, as subjects, are by far the largest category in the entire Ulmann collection. They include adult men ranging in age from their twenties to very old. When the "subset" descriptions are applied to this general category, the following "types" appear.
MEN, Urban, are formal studio portraits of sophisticated, upper and middle class men and professionals, including authors, editors, actors, artists, and musicians, with most images made from the waist-up. Most are pictured in the businessman's or gentlemen's "uniform" of the time: a jacket, vest, and tie. Some wear an artistic smock or laboratory coat. The clothing styles range from very formal-looking early twentieth-century suits to more modern, relaxed outfits common in the late 1920s. Younger men in this later time period are shown in rolled-up shirtsleeves and open collars. The subjects sometimes hold pens or books, musical instruments, or stand next to laboratory furniture or painting easels, giving a clue as to their profession. Lighted cigarettes seem to have been a favorite prop. Urban, African American MEN are very few in number, the writer James Weldon Johnson, being one. There are also several unidentified and important-looking African men in what appear to be traditional robes.
MEN, Country (primarily Caucasian), and MEN, Country, African American, are photographed in rural outdoor settings. Good examples are photographs numbered 2684 through 2711, and 2769 through 2800. Farmers, blacksmiths, dockworkers, fishermen, carpenters, among others, are shown with the tools of their trades. The men look as if they just came in from the field, their clothes and faces covered in dust. Or, they can be wearing clean, pressed jackets, shits, and ties, as of ready for church or company. Whether clean or dusty, the clothes and hats are tattered and well-worn, the jackets and shirts have numerous patches. Several images are of African America n MEN in "chain gangs," working in groups along a roadside wearing striped prison uniforms and leg chains; Caucasian guards with rifles stand at the side. Regardless of what the men wear or what they are doing, as captured through Ulmann's lens, these "types" have great dignity and character.
WOMEN is the second largest category, although it is less than twenty percent of the size of the MEN category. They include adult women ranging in age from their twenties to very old. When the "subset" descriptions are applied, the following "types" emerge.
WOMEN, Urban (primarily Caucasian) and WOMEN, Urban, African American are formal studio portraits of sophisticated upper and middle class women and professionals, including editors, authors, artists, actresses, and musicians. They display a wide range of costume, jewelry, and hairstyles from early twentieth-century formal gowns to the flapper-style and more modern, comfortable-looking dresses of the late 1920's. These later styles include man-tailored suits as well as artistic, embroidered gowns and robes; this latter group includes several portraits of Bertha Goudy, type designer and co-proprietor of the Village Press.
WOMEN, Country, and WOMEN, Country, African American correspond to descriptions, above, of Country MEN. The women wear housedresses and aprons or remove their aprons when dressed for company or church, adding a hat. There is an especially notable set of images of young women and girls, grouped in numbers 818 through 1013 (among others.) African American WOMEN are also shown working outside of the home, for instance, at tables bundling asparagus, or in the asparagus or cotton fields.
Types for CHILDREN are as follows.
CHILDREN, Urban, are Caucasian. Some of these children are identified, including Evelyn Necarsulmer (born 1908, the only child of Ulmann's only sibling), and Ethel Durant, the daughter of historian Will Durant.
CHILDREN, Country or CHILDREN, African American are some of Ulmann's more notably beautiful and sensitive images. She photographed groups simply posed for the camera, or seen at a swimming hole or at a wagon with books. Some were captured with their grandparents or riding in a car. Good examples of this genre appear in images 1600 through 1640, among others
GROUPS (two or more) includes portraits that are of two or more people, and were thus impossible to include in the other categories because most of the groups are combinations of MEN, WOMEN, or CHILDREN. Many are children, as noted above. There are two other prominent subsets of GROUPS. One is Country couples, presumably husbands and wives, (images numbered 2475 through 2725, among others), and are mostly elderly people with expressive faces reflecting lives of poverty and years of hard work. The second group are photographs of Martha Graham and her troupe, the Martha Graham Dancers, captured at work in stage costumes and posed as if in the middle of a dance piece.
LANDSCAPES: a subject was considered a landscape if the overall emphasis was an outside environment, usually with a horizon line. Some landscapes include people, such as a farmer pushing a plow behind a horse, for example, but the landscape is the primary subject, rather than the person.
STILL LIFES: a subject was considered a still life when it focused on inanimate objects or parts of the human figure (hands, for instance). In some instances, small courtyards or doorways were also classified as still lifes because the content, composition, and light suggested something more intimate than a landscape
OTHER: a few miscellaneous items in the collection include what appear to be copied photographs of Ulmann family photographs, such as a small image of a Civil War era soldier. In addition, there are a number of empty mats that were signed by the editors who are photographed in the 1925 American Editors book. The fate of the missing photographs is unknown. However, it is possible these images were sent to an engraver when the book was printed and were never re-united with their mats.
Arrangement
Photographs were assigned consecutive numbers upon their arrival at the Society. They are filed by number, but an item-level database can be searched by subject term. Most photographs are of unidentifed people; a list of identified subjects appears in the container list below.
Boyd, James, 1888-1944 -- Portraits; Brenner, Victor D. (Victor David), 1871-1924 -- Portraits; Columbia University. -- College of Physicians and Surgeons -- Faculty -- Portraits; Cornell, Katharine, 1893-1974-- Portraits; Crowninshield, Frank, 1872-1947 -- Portraits; Galsworthy, John, 1867-1933 -- Portraits; Gish, Lillian, 1893-1993 -- Portraits; Glasgow, Ellen Anderson Gholson, 1873-1945 -- Portraits; Graham, Martha -- Portraits; Green, Paul, 1894-1981 -- Portraits; Hapgood, Norman, 1868-1937 -- Portraits; Hendrick, Burton Jesse, 1870-1949 -- Portraits; Johns Hopkins University. -- School of Medicine -- Faculty -- Portraits; Johnson, James Weldon, 1871-1938 -- Portraits; Moore, Marianne, 1887-1972 -- Portraits; Sell, Henry Blackman -- Portraits; Van Doren, Carl, 1885-1950 -- Portraits; Walsh, Richard J. (Richard John), b. 1886 -- Portraits; Wells, Thomas B. (Thomas Bucklin), 1875-1944 -- Portraits; Wright, Richardson Little, 1887-1961 -- Portraits; African Americans -- Portraits; Appalachians (People) -- Portraits; Celebrities -- United States --Portraits; Decorative arts -- Southern States; Editors -- United States -- Portraits; Handicraft -- Southern States; Indians of North America -- Portraits; Monks -- United States -- Portraits; Nuns -- United States -- Portraits; Photographic prints; Photogravures; Platinum prints
  Scope and Contents note
  A list of identified sitters follows, with a brief identification, if known, and the number of photographs in parentheses.
  - Abbott, Lawrence F., Editor, The Outlook (6)
  - Abel, John J., Professor of Pharmacology, Johns Hopkins University (3)
  - Adams, Henry Sherman, Editor, The Spur (8)
  - Adler, Felix, philosopher and founder of Ethical Culture Society (2)
  - Anderson, Sherwood, writer
  - Baer, William Stevenson, Associate Professor of Clinical Orthopedic Surgery, Johns Hopkins University (14)
  - Baetjer, Frederick Henry, Associate Professor of Clinical Roentgenology, Johns Hopkins University
  - Barker, Lewellys Franklin, Professor of Clinical Medicine, Johns Hopkins University (2)
  - Barnes, Margaret Ayers, 1886-1967 (5)
  - Bata Kindai Amgoza Lo Bagolo (13)
  - Bennett, John
  - Bloodgood, Joseph Colt, Associate Professor of Clinical Surgery, Johns Hopkins University (10)
  - Bloodyoor, Howland(4)
  - Blue, Chief Samuel (2)
  - Boggs, Thomas Richmond, Associate Professor of Clinical Medicine, Johns Hopkins University (3)
  - Boyd, James, 1888-1944, writer (17)
  - Bradford, Gamaliel, 1863-1932, American biographer (2)
  - Brenner, Victor David, 1871-1924, sculptor (11)
  - Bridges, Robert, Editor, Scribner's (18)
  - Broedel, Max, Associate Professor of Art as Applied to Medicine, Johns Hopkins University (4)
  - Burton-Opitz, Russell, Associate Professor of Physiology, Columbia University
  - Butler, Nicholas Murray, President, Columbia University (6)
  - Canby, William Seidel, Editor, The Saturday Review of Literature (3)
  - Chase, Edna Wooman, Editor, Vogue (4)
  - Cobb, Irvin S. (5)
  - Coolidge, Calvin, President of the United States (2)
  - Coolidge, Grace Goodhue, 1879-1957 (Mrs. Calvin Coolidge) (2)
  - Cornell, Katharine, actress (31)
  - Cosgrave, John O'Hara, Editor, the Sunday World (3)
  - Coy, George J., Registrar of the Medical Department, Johns Hopkins University (5)
  - Croly, Herbert, Editor, The New Republic
  - Cross, Wilbur, Editor, The Yale Review
  - Crowe, Samuel James, Associate Professor of Clinical Laryngology, Johns Hopkins University (2)
  - Crowell, Merle, Editor, The American Magazine (2)
  - Crowninshield, Frank, Editor, Vanity Fair (20)
  - Cullen, Thomas Stephen, Professor of Clinical Gynecology, Johns Hopkins University (5)
  - Currie, Barton W., editor, Ladies Home Journal
  - Cutting, Elizabeth Brown, editor, North American Review (2)
  - Darrach, William, Professor of Clinical Surgery, Columbia University (3)
  - Davis, Robert H., Editor, Munsey's (4)
  - Dow, Arthur Wesley, 1857-1922, artist and theorist (4)
  - Durant, Ethel
  - Elliot, John Lovejoy
  - Farrar, John (Chipman), editor, The Bookman (6)
  - Finemen, Irving, writer (2)
  - Finney, John Miller Turpin, Professor of Clinical Surgery, Johns Hopkins University (8)
  - Follis, Richard Holden, M.D., Associate Professor of Clinical Surgery, Johns Hopkins University (2)
  - Forbes, Esther (3)
  - Fordyce, John A., Professor of Dermatology and Syphilology, Columbia University (9)
  - Frost, Robert (7)
  - Futcher, Thomas Barnes, Associate Professor of Clinical Medicine, Johns Hopkins University
  - Gale, Zona (2)
  - Galsworthy, John, 1867-1933, English writer (14)
  - Garland, Hamlin, 1860-1940, writer (3)
  - Geraghty, John Timothy, Associate Professor Clinical Urology, Johns Hopkins University (6)
  - Gibson, Charles Dana, 1864-1944, illustrator (3)
  - Gies, William J., Professor Biological Chemistry, Columbia University (5)
  - Gilchrist, Thomas Caspar, Clinical Professor of Dermatology, Johns Hopkins University
  - Gish, Lillian (14)
  - Glasgow, Ellen, novelist (16)
  - Goodnow, Frank Johnson, President of Johns Hopkins University (3)
  - Goudy, Bertha, type designer (4)
  - Goudy, Frederic W., 1865-1947, type designer (5)
  - Graham, Martha, dancer (24)
  - Green, Paul Eliot, 1894-1981, writer, dramatist (13)
  - Hadden, Briton, Editor, Time
  - Haggard, Sewell, Editor, Everybody's
  - Hamman, Louis Virgil, M.D., Associate Professor of Clinical Medicine, Johns Hopkins University (2)
  - Hapgood, Norman, Editor, Hearst International (12)
  - Harriman, Karl Edwin, Editor, The Red Book Magazine (8)
  - Hendrick, Burton Jesse, Editor, The World's Work (14)
  - Herford, Oliver, editor, Life (2)
  - Hergesheimer, Joseph (2)
  - Heyward, Dubose, writer (3)
  - Hibbs, Russell A., Professor of Orthopedic Surgery, Columbia University (10)
  - Hoffman, Arthur Sullivant, Editor, Adventure
  - Holt, L. Emmett, Carpentier Professor of the Diseases of Children, Columbia University (5)
  - Hooker, Donald Russell, Associate Professor of Physiology, Johns Hopkins University (2)
  - Howard, Virginia
  - Howell, William Henry, Professor of Physiology, Johns Hopkins University(10)
  - Howland, John, Professor of Pediatrics, Johns Hopkins University (5)
  - Huntington, George S., Professor of Anatomy, Columbia University (5)
  - Hurd, Henry Mills, Professor Emeritus of Psychiatry, Johns Hopkins University
  - Hurst, Fannie, 1889-1968, writer (2)
  - Jacobi, Abraham, Emeritus Professor of Diseases of Children, Columbia University (7)
  - Jaeger, Charles H., Ulmann's husband, Physician, and Assistant Professor of Orthopaedics, Columbia University (8)
  - Jobling, James W., Professor of Pathology, Columbia University (8)
  - Johnson, James Weldon poet, diplomat, songwriter, and anthologist (23)
  - Jones, Walter, Professor of Physiological Chemistry, Johns Hopkins University (12)
  - Keller, Helen (3)
  - Kelly, Howard Atwood, Professor Emeritus of Gynecology, Johns Hopkins University
  - La Farge, Oliver, writer (7)
  - Lamb, Charles Rollinson, 1860-1942 (5)
  - Lambert, Adrian Van Sindern, Associate Professor of Surgery, Columbia University (2)
  - Lambert, Samuel W., Professor of Clinical Medicine and Dean, Columbia University
  - Lee, Frederic S., Dalton Professor of Physiology, Columbia University (2)
  - Lewis, Sinclair (3)
  - Lewisohn, Mrs. Sam (Margaret Seligman) (8)
  - Long, Ray, editor, The Cosmopolitan (2)
  - Lord, Jere Williams, Clinical Professor of Dermatology, Johns Hopkins University
  - Lorimer, George Horace, Editor in chief, Saturday Evening Post (3)
  - Mac Callum, William George, Baxley Professor of Pathology, Johns Hopkins University (2)
  - Maclean, Charles Thomas Agnew, Editor, Popular Magazine (5)
  - Martha Graham Dancers (6)
  - McClure, Samuel Sidney, Editor, McClure's (3)
  - Menken, H.L., Editor, The American Mercury
  - Meyer, Adolf, M.S., LL.D., Professor of Psychiatry, Johns Hopkins University (4)
  - Millay, Edna St. Vincent
  - Moore, Marianne, 1887-1972, poet (12)
  - Moore, Marianne, 1887-1972, poet, with her mother, Mary Warner Moore (6)
  - Mumford, Lewis, American writer and critic (3)
  - Nathan, George Jean, editor, The American Mercury (2)